portal figure, a giant within
Science fiction and fantasy also actually.
Your relationship with her
as a writer.
The first thing I read by Le Guin was enough
In the middle school actually
An old book called it is called "The World is called Forest".
An allegory of the Vietnam War, it did not understand that time.
At that time I read everything that was science fiction.
But it was probably the first lit neighbor
socially and ethically challenging
Mainly because it is so
What is the name?
Ambivalent.
It is probably the charm of it.
Now we have held you who are looking at the halter because why are you just two here?
You may wonder that.
Andreas works with the publisher, Federative's publisher, and Jens has illustrated the book.
Exactly, that's why you are here.
But now one might wonder why this particular book when Ursula K. Le Guin has written quite a lot
For a long time, I think this book came in 1974 and you may correct me if it is wrong
But I want to remember that they were so that it was first released in English.
So why exactly this book
by Ursula's big publication?
Yes, you may think it is a bit strange that the publisher that Federatives publishes a science fiction book.
Federative's publisher otherwise publishes the most books about
different forms of workers' struggle or organization.
But even more recently quite a lot of fiction within that genre.
And this is where this fits in as it is a
perhaps the best of literature, at least as I know, realized
vision of a society organized from below
The starting title was the best.
As discussion groups are called: "Karatebook".
It is almost an impossible title to translate from English.
"The Dispossessed".
It is not like a comfortable term in Swedish.
"The uninhabited" is as close as you can get to involve all these details at the same time.
"Shevek" was a pretty flat title.
Because instead of focusing on what is happening,
On the act itself, on everything it becomes that you focus on the main character.
And it remove a large part of the book
Well, be one of the arguments for change.
Researcher...
I don't know what to say.
You can take this!
One of the reasons why it is difficult to summarize the book is that it takes place in
Two parallel time tracks.
I don't want to reveal too much about the action here of course
Because they can stand on their own legs, I think.
But it starts with the main character Shevek
A scientist
make their exit from
This anarchist planet Anarres to go back to the mother planet
A planet is very similar to spring called ancestry.
For us acquaintances and hierarchical
Society.
I remember the stage when he walks on Shoppinggatan.
It is very memorable, how he reacts to this, how he meets from his
comprehension of the world and conviction of the world and
Coming to the learf it is very striking I think.
Did you have anything more?
No, drive on!
So some
English editions have the title
"The Dispossessd - an Ambigous Utopia"
And it is sometimes described as a utopia.
Utopias always have two ends so to speak
But is sometimes described as a utopia.
How do you think about this with ambiguous or ambigous?
I'm going to throw myself in this.
That's the absolute best thing about the book.
That is what, in my opinion, does it
And make it so devilishly readable.
Le Guin was an anarchist himself.
over all ideals.
There are flaws everywhere.
So I would squeeze in that as a book it doesn't seem to be ...
Given, that is, it is difficult because Le Guin wrote "Left Hand of Darkness"
One of the most classic feminist scifi works.
Should one measure it up to it is not about feminism at all
However, Le Guin as a writer
She had her opinions and it shines through her authorship, all her authorship.
So even though the book may not have it as a focus, you can see a lot
details from feminism or wider feminism in the book.
Things that are in as
Watches first and on anarres
so regardless of gender you work with what you are suitable for
And on Anarres (urban) he comes to this research world where everyone is men.
I even think they say, now I spoil a little here, but they say
That women do not have the ability to deeper thoughts or abstractly thought in that way.
Where the women are wives.
Yes, or mistresses.
Yes exactly but they don't have it ...
It becomes very clear there anyway.
Absolutely.
Can I just squeeze in there?
So now there is a risk of spoilers too and then you have to cut the iron.
And that is now 80 and she has ailments.
She doesn't really understand the youth anymore but
She is idealized and she doesn't like it.
Yes, it's amazing.
I'm looking forward to it.
It's a pretty moderate edition.
It is very nice.
There is also a nice explanation for why the book is green.
Looks like it does.
But this is the first Swedish illustrated edition?
Yes.
Ever in the history of the entire universe.
And the first time the short story was published in the same volume in Swedish.
And the first time Karin Tidbeck has written the preface to this one.
And the first time the cover is green.
It is the first of a lot.
We might be able to talk a little about how you got this assignment
And how you felt about it when you got the question.
I don't really know how it went.
You can tell you a little about it.
So illustrates the book.
Yes.
Thanks.
I received an email from Andreas asking about ...
I would just cover from the beginning.
But.
The thing is that when someone asks "Hi, want to illustrate your absolute favorite book?"
It's like.
He could pay me in carrots.
I had done that too.
And I also the world's worst negotiator so I was very like "sure, certain shit in the payment !!"
Now we should say then because we are owned by a trade union.
So I get paid.
No, but Jens said yes I do.
But I intend to illustrate it and
If not taking my illustration, I intend to break into the print shop and put them in myself.
Damn how disturbing I sound when you say so.
We are very happy that you wanted to illustrate it, Jens.
Thanks!
There's alot
both cover and illustrations in science fiction back in history where one has often focused on
A little more classic science fiction element.
It is common with spaceships.
Now there is not so much spaceship in this.
It's not so much radiation guns and so on.
Unfortunately!
But as you approach this assignment.
For your illustrations have other focus.
As I don't think anyone will see.
Now arrears ...
Nice that you can say this then.
So we so!
Yes.
Great!
But there was deep anxiety and a lot of notes.
I filled a notepad with that.
To conclude.
I think of some ...
If you get to choose two favorite illustrations as well as say a little more about.
What is it?
It is sickly difficult for a large of the illustration job is just about
Be able to weave the whole book together with different illustrations.
My absolute favorite It is associated with the favorite chapter and it is the middle chapter.
Where the two chairs will represent these two worlds that meet
and Shevek's complete customerness.
Once again we should not spoil too much.
The second is the image to "the day before the revolution",
Which was also hugely difficult.